# Deepak Kandel

**(**+1)-585-410-8148

 $\bowtie$  dk6012@rit.edu

**♥** Rochester, NY, USA

https://github.com/kandeldeepak46

# SUMMARY

Artificial intelligence and data science practitioner with hands-on experience in image processing, computer vision, and machine learning from research & development to production. Currently, I am experimenting with developing novel Bayesian algorithms to estimate uncertainty, incorporate self-awareness, and support continual/lifelong learning for streaming data to address real-world computer vision problems. Besides lab work, I like experimenting with training and fine-tuning Large Language Models (LLMs) on customs datasets.

## **EDUCATION**

## Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Imaging Science

Aug 2022 — Present

Chester F. Carlson Center For Imaging Science, Rochester Institute of Technology

Rochester, NY, U.S.A.

• Courses: Image Processing & Computer Vision, Deep Learning

#### Bachelor's Degree, Electronics & Communication Engineering

Nov 2015 — Sep 2019

DoECE, Pulchowk Campus, Institute of Engineering, Tribhuvan University

Pulchowk, Lalitpur, Nepal

- Merit-based 4-year scholarship
- Courses: Artificial Intelligence, Data Mining, Mathematics (Calculus, Linear Algebra, Probability & Statistics, Numerical Methods, Discrete Structures)

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

Continual Learning, Large Language Model (LLM), Bayesian Learning, and Uncertainty Estimation

## WORK EXPERIENCE

## Graduate Research Assistant

June 2023 — Present

Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY, U.S.A.

• Experimenting with variational inference for lifelong/continual learning

### Graduate Teaching Assistant

Aug 2022 — May 2023

Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY, U.S.A.

- GTA For Probability & Statistics with Python
- GTA For Fundamentals of Imaging Science

#### Machine Learning Engineer

Dec 2020 — July 2022

Evolve

Kathmandu, Bagmati, Nepal

- Designed and developed a Multi-Store-Multi-Item demand quantity prediction system using ARIMA, prophet, Temporal Fusion Transformer, and LightGBM
- Developed the product recommendation engine for FMCG products using Autoencoders and LightFM
- Developed in-house outlet localization and Automatic Route Generator (ARC) API based on geo-location for optimized distribution of goods

## **Data Scientist**

Mar 2020 — Dec 2020

Docsumo

Kathmandu, Bagmati, Nepal

- Information retrieval from tax, invoice, and bill documents and digitization of non-digital PDF (bank statements, W2, & W9) forms using advanced OCR techniques
- Contributed to face recognition system for verification of documents with Indian driving license [KYC for banks and Insurance companies]
- Improving the image quality: skewness detection, correction, and enhancements with computer vision and image processing
- Developed and deployed the AI applications in Google Cloud Platforms

Data Science Intern Oct 2019 — Feb 2019

Neoteric Lalitpur, Bagmati, Nepal

- Sales Data Analysis, Weekly Sales Revenue Estimation using Deep-AR and ARIMA, Market Segmentation
- Laptops Brands Classification using Transfer Learning

## Technical Coordinator & AI Fellowship Instructor

May 2018 – Feb 2019

LOCUS

Lalitpur, Bagmati, Nepal

- Introduced attendees to python, Conda environment, NumPy, matplotlib, and pandas for data interpretation and visualization
- Project demos on face recognition system and CNN-based MNIST handwritten digit recognition
- End-to-end implementation of iris flower classification and titanic survival prediction served with RESTful APIs

## **PROJECTS**

- Training and Fine-Tuning Large Language Model (LlaMa-2) for NeurIPS Large Language Model Efficiency Challenge
- Assessment of U-Net for Brain Tumor Segmentation with Gaussian Noise on Training Data
- Book Recommendation System based on Hybrid Methods of Matrix Filtering
- Instance Segmentation of Buildings using Deep CNN For Paint Color Visualization
- Near-Real Time Objection Recognition using Pre-trained Deep Neural Network
- Sentiment Analysis of Google Play applications reviews with Fine-Tuning of BERT
- Digital Image Halftoning and Removal Using Fast Fourier Transform
- MRI Image Denoising using Markov Chain Monte Carlo and Non-Local Means

# TECHNICAL STACKS

**Programming** python

Deep Learning / Computer Vision TensorFlow, PyTorch

LLM and Gen AILlaMa-2, RAG, LangChain, Prompt EngineeringMachine Learningscikit-learn, NumPy, pandas, matplotlib, SciPy

Image Processing OpenCV

Project Management Gitlab, Jira, Confluence

Miscellaneous IATEX, Cloud Computing, Git, Bash, Flask, Docker

# AWARDS & HONORS

#### Scholarship/Assistantship for Ph.D.

• Received merit-based scholarship at RIT to pursue Ph.D. in Imaging Science

#### Full Scholarship for Undergraduate Studies

• Government-funded 4-year Scholarship For Engineering Studies (4% acceptance rate)

# Training's & Crash Course

## Data Analytics & Machine Intelligence (DAMI)

 $\mathbf{Jan}\ \mathbf{2019}$ 

• 15-day workshop organized by ICTC Center, Institute of Engineering (IoE), Pulchowk Campus, in association with IIT Delhi

#### Kickstart for AI & Machine Learning

Jan 2018 - Jun 2018

• Took part in the workshop by AI Dev Nepal to get a kickstart on the basics and AI and Machine Learning

#### Workshop on Set Farm

Jan 2018 - Jun 2018

• Workshop on set farm Nepal for intelligence in farming & agriculture with robotics, organized by Purwanchal Campus Dharan, Pulchowk Campus, Nepal, & Washington State University, USA